Hazaq Naiem



PROFILE

Enthusiastic about cloud technology with over a decade of experience, I bring advanced proficiency in cloud, Devops, and enterprise solutions. As a seasoned solution builder for diverse service providers, I have successfully collaborated with a spectrum of organizations, including large enterprises, start-ups, banks, and government entities. Engaging regularly with development and technical teams, I specialize in constructing optimal solutions for mission-critical workloads, ensuring seamless application integration, and delivering successful outcomes.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Well-versed with cloud computing with extensive experience in cloud architecture.
- Experienced in deployment of highly available applications, and migrating critical workloads.
- Proficient in a broad spectrum of Devops tools and technologies.
- Proven record of excellent troubleshooting, analytical and problem-solving skills.
- Certified in data engineering skills such as data integrations, pipelines and transformation.
- Skilled in advanced networking concepts, including designing and managing secure, scalable network architectures.
- Proficient in troubleshooting complex technical issues, with a strong ability to diagnose, resolve, and prevent system and application problems.
- Proven customer-facing experience in engaging with clients to assess technical requirements.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Cloud Architect

April 2021 - Present

Crayon

Dubai, United Arab Emirates

As a cloud Architect at a leading software and cloud distribution company, I play a pivotal role in championing cloud infrastructure, DevOps, and migration initiatives across the MEA region. My responsibilities extend to providing robust support to both new and existing customers, as well as collaborating closely with our partners. Within the MEA architect community, I take the lead in steering our cloud practice, demonstrating a deep commitment to advancing our expertise in this domain.

Responsibilities:

- Design and build cloud architectures to support customer's unique requirements with an emphasis on security and automation.
- Mobilize customer migrations by creating and designing Landing Zones, based on best participants
 to include centralize identity and access management, and establishes governance rules for security
 and compliance.
- Perform infrastructure discovery and assessment, identify potential challenges, and build a cloud migration strategy for our customers.
- Conduct migration readiness assessment for enterprise customers and build a business case for the cloud migration.
- Troubleshoot common technical issues, conduct well architect reviews, and help mitigate security, operational and performance challenges for the customer.
- Build project documentations such as high-level solution architecture, scope of work, technical write-ups and govern the project till the delivery.
- Conduct immersion day, workshops, demos and build proof of concepts for customers and partners.

Dec 2020 - April 2021

Moro Hub

Dubai, United Arab Emirates

Moro is a digital transformation entity that offers Digital Services, Data Center Services, Managed Services, Professional Services, cloud, and Business Center Services to enterprises across the Public & Private sectors in UAE and the region.

Responsibilities:

- Interact with the customer to understand the technical requirement and work on possible solutions and services.
- Evaluate customer workloads and interact with infrastructure and development teams to find contingencies and bottle necks within the workloads.
- Work with different subject-matter experts to architect a finalized solution that befits the customer's requirement.
- Create root cause analysis reports with different team of the enterprise applications and create recommendations to avoid future failures.
- Build proof of concepts for the customer to evaluate and to get familiarized with the Moro solutions and services.
- Conduct training sessions and workshops on cloud platforms for existing and new customers.

Senior System Architect / Integration Engineer Integra Technologies

March 2016 – Nov 2020 Dubai, United Arab Emirates

Integra Technologies is the first AWS Public Sector Partner in the Middle East and is also Advance partners with different open-source companies such as Red Hat, SUSE and Zimbra. Integra Technologies is focused on providing Amazon Web Services (AWS) and Linux-based business solutions to enterprises in the Middle East.

Responsibilities:

- Build and design applications that are highly available, scalable, and elastic, using open-source software and solutions.
- Responsible for designing, deploying, and maintaining Linux-based mission critical server and infrastructure for numerous clients spread across the Middle East.
- Researching, testing and bench-marking available open-source solutions to assess whether they are ready to meet the demands of our enterprise customers.
- Responsible for managing numerous AWS accounts for different customers, implementing security best practices, and performing cost optimizations.
- Automate system administration and application deployment tasks using CI/CD and other system orchestration tools to reduce operation time.
- Building architectures for workloads on AWS and migrating on-premises workloads to AWS.
- Respond to support calls and alerts from the monitoring system. Debug and troubleshoot production issues on live environments, provide remote and on-site support.

System Administrator Wathaaeq Services

Feb 2014 – March 2016 Sharjah, United Arab Emirates

Wathaaeq and Estemarat Services is a semi-government organization that processes documents for the ministry of labor and notary public.

Responsibilities:

• Configure and maintain centralized logging system for audit and security.

- Perform regular backups and upgrades on all production systems. Apply security patches on mission critical systems in case of a zero-day vulnerability.
- Work with the development team in managing and deploying Linux and Windows based applications.
- Assist technical support team with any server or client-side issues.
- Automating system administration tasks using bash and powershell scripting.
- Administration of Windows Server based IIS server hosting ASP.NET based corporate websites.

Technical Support

July 2013 - Jan 2014

Kest LLC

Sharjah, United Arab Emirates

Responsibilities:

- Configuring routers, switches, desktops and office equipment like scanners and printers at offices.
- Provide technical support to the users, monitoring, and maintenance of physical and virtual servers.
- Build and track IT asset and device inventory.
- Debug and troubleshoot applications, report any issues back to the developers.

CERTIFICATIONS		
AWS Certified Data Engineer – Associate	Dubai, UAE	Jun 2024
AWS Certified Advanced Networking - Specialty	Dubai, UAE	Dec 2023
Dynatrace Associate Certification	Dubai, UAE	July 2023
Red Hat Certified Engineer (RHEL 8)	Dubai, UAE	April 2022
Red Hat Certified System Administrator (RHEL 8)	Dubai, UAE	April 2022
Certified Kubnerneties Administrator (CKA)	Dubai, UAE	Nov 2021
Microsoft Certified Azure Administration Associate	Dubai, UAE	Sep 2021
Microsoft Certified Azure Fundamentals	Dubai, UAE	July 2021
AWS Certified DevOps Engineer – Professional	Dubai, UAE	May 2020
AWS Certified Solution Architect-Professional	Dubai, UAE	Oct 2019
AWS Certified Developer – Associate	Dubai, UAE	Nov 2019
AWS SysOps Administrator – Associate	Dubai, UAE	Nov 2019
AWS Certified Solutions Architect-Associate	Dubai, UAE	Nov 2019

EDUCATION

BS in Electronic Engineering (Major in Computer Systems)

Sep 2009 – Jun 2013

CGPA: 3.69 / 4

International Islamic University, Islamabad, Pakistan